Finding Aid for Hemlock of Michigan records, 1989-2006
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Hemlock of Michigan records 1989-2006
Hemlock (Society). Hemlock of Michigan.
6.3 linear feet
93853 Bj 2
Michigan chapter of organization established to support right of terminally ill adults to be able to choose either passive or active voluntary euthanasia for themselves. Organizational records, including correspondence, newsletters, membership lists, and clippings and articles about organization.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group came from the organization (donor no. 8057 ) in multiple accessions.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research, except for the membership lists which are closed for 20 years from the date of their creation.
Hemlock of Michigan is an educational, non-profit organization that supports the right of terminally ill adults to die with dignity and self-respect. Therefore, the organization supports the rights of individuals to choose for themselves either a passive or active voluntary euthanasia. This chapter of the National Hemlock Society was formed on September 23, 1989 at the home of Janet and Ray Good when sixteen people met to form a steering committee for the Michigan chapter. Based upon the principle that terminally ill persons should be able to determine the manner, means, and timing of their death, Hemlock also supports the individual's right to refuse artificial support which only prolongs the process of dying. Some of the objectives of the organization, beyond educating the public to the principle of active voluntary euthanasia, include support for legislation that would permit physicians to aid the terminally ill in dying. Hemlock of Michigan disbanded in 2006.
The record group includes organizational records, including correspondence, newsletters, and membership lists. Other files document the relationship of Hemlock of Michigan with the national organization as well as its activities as an advocacy group to the Michigan Legislature. Of significance are the several folders of clippings and articles on the activities of the organization and on the general subject of death and dying.
Subjects:
Euthanasia--Michigan.; Hemlock (Society). Hemlock of Michigan.; Right to die--Michigan.; Suicide--Michigan.
- Organization
  - Formation of Hemlock of Michigan (Box 1)
  - Board Meetings, Financial Reports, Memos among Board Members, 1990-2006, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Newsletters (Box 1)
  - Membership Lists
    - 1989 (Box 1)
    - 1990s-2000s (Box 7)
      (lists are closed for 20 years from the date of creation)
  - Public Meetings and Fund Raisers (Box 1)
  - Official Handouts and Brochures (Box 1)
  - Book Sales (Box 1)
  - Relations with Beier & Howlett (Law Firm) (Box 1)
  - Selection of letters to & from members and private individuals (surname blacked out) (Box 1)
  - Janet Good, founder of Hemlock of Michigan (Box 1)
- Relations with Outside Organizations & Individuals
  - National Hemlock Society/Hemlock USA
    - General, 1990-2000, 5 folders (Box 1)
    - General, 2001-2006, 5 folders (Box 2)
    - Annual Reports (Box 2)
    - Newsletters
      - Chapter Leaders, 1990-1993 (Box 2)
      - Chapter Leaders Resource, 1994-2005, 3 folders (Box 2)
      - National, 1988-2006, 6 folders (Box 2)
    - Other Publications (Box 2)
  - Other Chapters of Hemlock (Box 2)
  - Other Death with Dignity Organizations, 1991-1992 (Box 2)
  - Other Death with Dignity Organizations, 1993-2006, 8 folders (Box 3)
  - Presentations & Speeches (Box 3)
  - Dr. Jack Kevorkian (Box 3)
  - Libraries (Box 3)
- Political Activity
  - Legislative, Commission on Death & Dying
    - General, 1991-1993, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - General, 1993-1995, 4 folders (Box 4)
    - Detroit, November 8, 1993 (Box 4)
    - Midland, November 9, 1993 (Box 4)
    - Grand Rapids, November 10, 1993 (Box 4)
    - Traverse City, November 12, 1993 (Box 4)
    - Final Report, 1994 (Box 4)
  - Judicial, 1990-1995, 6 folders (Box 4)
  - Other State Programs, e.g. Wash. Initiative 119 (Box 4)
  - Letters (Box 4)
- Clippings and Articles
  - 1992- 1989 with some earlier clippings, 4 folders (Box 4)
  - 1993, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - 1994, 7 folders (Box 5)
  - 1995, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - 1996, 6 folders (Box 5)
  - 1997, 12 folders (Box 5)
  - 1998, 6 folders (Box 5)
  - 1998, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - 1999, 5 folders (Box 6)
  - 2000, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - 2001 (Box 6)
  - 2002 (Box 6)
  - 2003 (Box 6)
  - 2003 (Box 6)
  - 2004 (Box 6)
  - 2005 (Box 6)
  - 2006 (Box 6)